Hi. I'm Rowena, a
Senior Program Manager
in the Systems Productivity and
Reporting Team in Google Cloud.
As a project manager,
you'll find that
you're not actually
the direct manager of
people in their roles.
The key soft skill
to have here is
around influence; influencing
without authority.
It's the ability to be able to
communicate with people
and make sure that
they understand your
goals and objectives and
take them along on a shared
vision and shared journey.
When I first became
a project manager,
one of the mistakes that I
often made was trying to do
everything for myself
and not asking for help.
Over the course of the
last couple of years,
I've really learned how
to delegate and work
with others as part
of a team to make
sure that I'm effectively
managing a project as
a project manager
regardless of whether I
have management or authority
over the project team,
and allowing those SMEs to
really do what they're
really good at.
Delegating for me in my
day-to-day role looks like this:
I try to find subject matter
experts or people that
really enjoy doing a
specific something
that may not actually
be their role.
One of the best
pieces of advice I
ever got from a
mentor was around
finding people in the
organization that
enjoy doing something and
delegating your work to them.
That way you can focus
on overall project
or program management
without having to get
bogged down in the weeds by
certain details that
actually you might not enjoy
doing or someone else
really enjoys doing.
Psychological safety
is really important in
teams because it brings
diversity of thought
to the table.
One thing that I'm really
working on is making sure
that we practice
inclusive meetings.
An example of that could
be in a meeting if
you notice that
one or two participants
are usually quiet
or don't speak up,
try to encourage
them to be a part
of the conversation. Even better,
have a coffee with
them before and
ask them what they think
of the upcoming topic.
Encourage them to bring
those ideas to the table.
Having diversity of thought
in the room is so important.
Otherwise, you're
going to end up
with one person in the room
constantly just
bringing their thoughts
and ideas to the table.
That's not very diverse.
One thing with
psychological safety
is this partnership with
mentorship and sponsorship.
To delegate, I make sure
that I sponsor people.
I make sure that I showcase
their best quality work across
the whole project team.
It's really important
for morale.
On the other side
with mentorship,
if there's a junior team member
on a team that
maybe doesn't have
the experience or isn't
as confident speaking up,
I usually delegate
smaller tasks to
them to build up
their confidence or
delegate something that they
might actually consider to
be fun that's not in their
normal day-to-day work.
Finding those unique balances is
the best way to delegate
and prioritize.